Welcome to the section on quantifying costs.
Energy is expensive.
It's a commodity that costs many
percent of the entire economic output.
So when we make choices-- choices, say,
between coal power and solar power,
between electric vehicles and
conventional vehicles-- those choices
have profound consequences.
And they inevitably involve trade-offs,
trade-offs about how much we spend now,
and trade-offs about how much we
protect the environment and human lives.
The fundamental way that in this
course we will wrap those trade-offs up
is by quantifying the overall cost.
In this course, most of our
work on quantifying cost
will use two techniques-- levelized
cost and cost of mitigation.
Levelized cost refers to the
cost for a single alternative,
and the cost that calculates different costs
put together across time-- for example,
the initial cost of a power plant
and then the operating cost of it over time.
There's a way to combine those
to produce a single average cost.
That's called the levelized cost.
The cost of mitigation is always about
a choice between two alternatives.
Suppose you have one power
plant that costs a lot
but doesn't admit very much pollution,
and another power plant which costs
less but does emit more pollution.
You can compare the two
alternatives and calculate
the cost of saving pollution, which
might be in cost per ton of pollution
you saved.
Those are the two fundamental
techniques we'll use,
and we want you to learn how
to use those across the course
and be familiar with calculating them
for everything from large power plants
to individual choices you
might make around your house.
The two topics are the levelized
cost for a single alternative,
and the cost of mitigation,
which always comes
when you compare two alternatives.
We will teach you formulas that allow you
to calculate the levelized cost and cost
of mitigation with very high precision.
You can calculate it to 1%.
But we also want you to understand all
the limitations of these calculations.
These calculations include all
sorts of hidden uncertainties,
and we want you to at least know
what those uncertainties are.
One of the single most
important uncertainties
is the uncertainty hidden in the
interest or discount rate that's
used in the levelized cost formula.
We'll come back to that in detail
at the end of this section.
How much would you pay me for
the legally binding promise
that I would give you $1 a year from now?
Think about it.
Your answer should be less than $1.
$1 a year from now is worth less than
$1 today, and the amount that it's worth
less is called the discount rate.
If the discount rate is 10%, then you
should pay me $0.90 for my promise
of $1 a year from now.
The discount rate is the amount
that future costs or benefits are
discounted compared to current costs.
So why do we discount the future at all?
Here are three reasons.
The first is what's called pure hedonic time
preference, where hedonic
comes from hedonism, the fact
that you like pleasure.
So if I offer you the choice
of an ice cream cone today
or an ice cream cone a year from now,
you prefer the ice cream cone today
simply because, all else equal, you'd
rather have your pleasures today.
Second is uncertainty.
If I offer you that ice
cream cone a year from now,
you don't know for sure that
I'll be able to honor my offer.
Maybe I'll be dead, maybe you'll be dead,
maybe you won't like ice cream anymore.
There are all sorts of uncertainties.
That's a separate concept
from hedonic time preference.
It has to do with the fact that
you don't know for sure what
will happen in the future, but
you know much more certainly
what will happen now.
And that uncertainty about the
future is a fundamental reason
that we discount future costs and benefits.
We don't know for sure that
we're going to get them.
Then there's a third related
concept that doesn't directly
applied to our ice cream example, but does
apply whenever you're thinking about
something that costs a lot of money.
There's always something else you
could have done with that money,
and the fact that you don't do it represents
what's called an opportunity cost.
You've lost the opportunity to do
something else with that money,
like invest it in something that would
have produced more money over time.
And that tie to alternative
things you could have done with it
is yet another recent we
discount future costs.
Let's dig a little deeper into
opportunity cost and discounting.
Many people in the environmental community
would like to believe the discount
rate should be very low, almost 0,
because they want to justify investments
in energy- and pollution-saving
technologies.
I want to see investment
in those technologies, too,
but we need to take discounting
seriously and here's why.
Suppose that you think discount
rate should be extremely low.
For the sake of argument, say
you think they should be 0.
That means you should be willing to lend
me $1 now and be happy to get just $1
back in 5 years.
But this would be a great deal for
me because I can invest that dollar
in some super low-risk
government bond, for example,
and be certain to have more
money, say $1.20, in 5 years.
That means if you give me that loan,
I'm effectively just printing money.
This shows the opportunity
cost in stark terms.
Money in the future really
is worth less because there
are other things you could have done
with the money that give you certainty
of growing your money over time.
That is a fundamental
reason why we can't just
ignore the fact that there really
is monetary discounting over time.
So what's the right discount rate to
use in energy system calculations?
The answer is there is no right answer.
The different discount rates really
make sense for different individuals,
corporations, or governments
making the decisions.
Here are some examples.
Individuals in their own lives tend
to use pretty high discount rates
because there's lots of uncertainty and
people don't have the kind of certainty
of savings that a government does.
Think about a poor person,
maybe a starving person.
Their discount rate is
extremely high because they
have very few alternatives.
But a large, stable government
can have a very low discount rate
because they can safely wait for payback.
The main factor is simply the
opportunity cost of the investment.
Governments often use discount
rates around 5% or even lower.
A large company, like, say, Shell or Exxon,
can also use quite low discount
rates, close to a government rate,
because they make long-term
investments confident
their company will exist
10 or 20 years from now.
Think about a small, solar-powered
startup company or a company
doing fracking.
Those companies tend to
use shorter discount rates
because in a small startup, you don't know
for sure your company
will exist in 10 years,
and so you have to think shorter-term.
There's no right rate.
The rate depends on the
agent making the decision.
What you need to do is think
carefully about the way
the rate you choose in an energy system
calculation is suitable or not suitable
for the decision you're
trying to make or advise.
And think about the fact that that rate
can determine the answer to the energy
system analysis.
As a specific example, suppose
you want to supply energy
for some off-grid
application, and your choice
is solar with a battery backup
or a gasoline-powered generator.
Think about the difference between
these two systems and the way
that discount rate matters.
The solar system has a
much higher capital cost,
a much higher first purchase cost.
Gasoline generators are really cheap to buy,
but they have high operating cost
that depends on the cost of gasoline.
So which should you buy?
As you've learned in the
earlier part of this section,
you can calculate the levelized
cost of electricity for both
and choose whatever is lowest.
But the heart of that LCOE
calculation is the formula
that takes cost in future
years and converts them
to an equivalent current year cost.
In our formula, the discount rate
is a fixed percentage per year,
and it compounds, so the
value of a future dollar
decays exponentially in the
future as you see in this plot.
So that means if the rate is 10%, $1
a year from now is only worth $0.90
today.
And 10 years out, that dollar
is only worth $0.35 today.
The choice of discount rate
can determine the answer
to the solar versus generator question.
If you choose a high discount
rate, then the future costs
of gasoline, those operational
costs, don't look very important
because those costs are
in discounted dollars.
But if you choose a very low discount
rate, then the costs of gasoline
keep mounting up and you're
going to choose the solar system.
So the choice between
high and low discount rate
determined the choice of solar versus gas.
When discount rates are high, then
first capital costs look most important
and you'll choose the gas-powered generator.
But when discount rates are low, that
operating cost looked more important,
and you'll choose the solar-powered system.
The choice of discount rate turns
out to make an enormous difference
to climate policy, one of the
central topics of this course.
If you spend money to cut
carbon dioxide emissions now,
say by replacing a coal-fired plant
with solar power or nuclear power,
the benefits in terms
of reduced climate risks
come, as we will learn, in a distant future.
Many of the benefits are felt 100 years out.
So how do we value those benefits?
That depends in turn on discount rate.
And if you choose a typical
market discount rate,
then the distant future 100 years from now
looks almost completely unimportant.
Suppose, for example, you
choose a discount rate
of 5%, which is a common choice
for ordinary policy analysis.
At a discount rate of 5%, the
costs are discounted in 100 years
by a factor of 130 to 0.8%.
Does that make any sense?
It's a highly controversial question, one
that lies at the very heart of
disputes about climate policy.
Think about it in terms of human lives.
What would you choose between
saving one life today and 130 lives
100 years from now?
That's what it means to
use a discount rate of 5%.
What's the right number?
There's no easy answer.
You might be tempted to say,
of course, a life is a life.
130 lives are much more important.
But you can't be sure that
any action you do today
will actually save lives 130 years from now.
So even for lives we should apply
some discounting, I believe.
But how to do it?
Deeply unclear.
And in that single number of discount rate,
we hide many of the core disputes
that really matter in making decisions
about energy and environmental policy.
Because time and time again, our choice is
whether we want to spend money today
to reduce air pollution or climate
pollution which will
cause harm in the future.
And the distinction, the
cost benefit analysis,
that allows us to choose what to
do depends on the discount rate.
There's no right answer,
but you need to think
hard about what rate is right for the
kind of decisions you want to make
or the kind of advice you
want to give to policymakers.
In conclusion, don't take the
issue of discounting lightly.
Be skeptical of expert claims
that they know exactly what's
the right answer for discounting.
Perhaps the following anecdote
will help you think about the way
that underlying values
determine these choices
in ways that are not easy to incorporate
in a single number, a discount rate.
I've worked on energy and
environmental policy personally
for about half my life-- about 25 years.
And if I take the simplest
economic formulation
of what we call optimal climate
policy, which at its core
is a cost benefit analysis, and
according to the standard economic cost
benefit analysis, which has
discounting near its heart,
the reason that I and other people
are working to reduce CO2 emissions
now is because it will make people
a few percent richer in 100 years.
That's because the benefits
of cutting carbon emissions
are larger than the cost once
you've applied discounting.
But do I really do that?
Do I really think about it that way?
I can tell you honestly that I don't.
I would still think we should
reduce carbon emissions
and reduce the way we're
changing the environment, even
if it made everybody poorer 100 years
from now-- at least a little bit
poorer.
However, I think that discounting
is very useful and highly
relevant for making choices in one country
or one society in a
relatively short time period,
and we need to think analytically
about what the trade-offs are.
There's no right answer.
I encourage you to think about
what kind of discount rate
you think is right for the
actual problems at hand,
and be skeptical about
expert claims that people
know exactly what's the right rate.