Turning from these abstract
goals, here is a short run-through
of the course content.
First, energy system overview--
the flows and transformations
of energy in the economy,
both in the US and the world,
and a look at how the energy system has
changed over the last few centuries.
Second, calculating costs-- how to go
from a system's capital and operating
costs to the cost of the
product, say from the price
of a car, fuel, and insurance to the
average cost per kilometer you drive--
and how to calculate the cost of
reducing environmental harms--
say the cost of cutting carbon emissions
by buying a solar power system.
Third, environmental impacts-- air
pollution, climate change, land
use-- an introduction to
the science into the methods
for estimating impacts.
Fourth, two short but crucial
topics-- the abundance
of fossil fuels and a quick
introduction into the electricity grid.
Fifth, solar photovoltaic
power-- the physics
of how it works, how the
cost of a complete system
is built up from various components, how
and why costs have decreased over time.
Sixth, nuclear power-- the physics of how
it works, how the cost of a complete system
is built up from various components,
how and why costs have mostly
increased over time.
Seventh, energy efficiency and demand-- how
has the energy efficiency of some
important energy transformations
changed over the last century?
Why have we seen stunning improvements
in some cases and stagnation in others?
When do improvements in
energy efficiency cut demand,
and when do they increase it?
And finally, eighth, an
attempt at a synthesis.
What does this blizzard of facts mean
for the big energy system challenges?
This is a minimal intro,
not a comprehensive course.
Here are just some of the important topics
we have left out-- a deep
dive into fossil fuels, more
detail on the electric power grid--
perhaps the greatest engineering
achievement of the 20th century--
energy end uses such as transportation,
buildings, and industry, other energy
sources, such as wind, biofuels, fossil
fuels with carbon capture,
and hydropower, and finally,
electricity storage.
Finally, here are a few
guidelines and a warning about how
we will approach these topics.
First, we take a how-things-work,
descriptive approach in the hope
that you can gain a rough
mechanic's appreciation
for how a few key parts
of the energy system work.
How does a gas turbine work,
from compressor to combustion?
How are turbine blades made and assembled.
Detail rich, not theory rich-- our goal here
is to give you a sense of the
interplay of technology and design
that shapes important energy devices.
We want you to understand that no
energy technology stands alone.
Each is interwoven with a larger set
of technologies and supply chains.
And the goal of learning all of this
is to help you develop intuitions about
when innovation is easy,
and when it will be hard.
This course is opinionated.
That's the warning.
Energy is too messy and
too political to admit
the objective, value-neutral
presentation that might
work in an Introductory Physics course.
So we will let you hear our sharp judgments,
but we will provide clear flags about where
our judgment diverges from the mainstream,
and give you links to alternate opinions.
For example, we are more
optimistic than many
that nuclear power can provide a
high-intensity, environmentally benign
energy source for the 21st century.
But we will provide you with
an overview of the arguments
that nuclear power is too
expensive or dangerous,
and we'll give you pointers to sources
that make these arguments effectively.
We aim at misconceptions.
We don't want to waste your time
teaching you what you already know.
We will select material to aim at
based on known, common misconceptions
about the energy system.
And where possible, we will use the testing
in this course to understand
what common misconceptions are.
This course is driven by the
view that economics matters.
Some energy courses, particularly
those taught by physicists like me,
tend to focus on fundamental
technical feasibility
or on marvelous new technologies,
without paying attention
to what things cost.
Our view is that cost and cost effectiveness
are central to understanding
energy challenges.
All of the energy
challenges we deal with here
have multiple potential
solutions-- solutions that
could work from a standpoint of
pure physics and engineering.
But money matters.
The energy system is 5% or 10% of the
economy, depending on how you count it.
And solutions that work but cost, say,
10 times more than today's technology,
aren't solutions in a world
that has many problems that
need our attention and money.
Finally, history matters.
Some familiarity with the history
of previous energy transitions--
of the slow transition from biofuels to
coal, or of the stunningly fast switch
from horses to cars-- is
a necessary background
to any understanding of
the current energy system,
and how it might be transformed to one
that emits nearly zero carbon dioxide,
has a smaller land footprint,
and does less to poison the air.
Could this transformation
be accomplished in 20 years?
A century?
What technologies and
policies could speed it up?
Welcome to Energy Within
Environmental Constraints.
Dive in.
Have fun.
Calculate and debate.