The job of electricity
planner is to figure out
what generating capacity to build
and how to dispatch that capacity,
how to turn it on and off, in
response to changing loads.
We'll address that second
question first, economic dispatch,
and then turn back to the question of, what
are the most efficient plants to build?
Consider the problem of
efficiently dispatching
a set of pre-existing generators.
Imagine you're the operator.
The basic way to minimize
cost is to figure out,
for each generator, what it's
marginal cost of generation is.
That's, what's the cost of each
additional hour for which it
generates power?
Nothing to do with the cost
of turning it on and off
or the cost to build it, just the cost
to generate an extra hour of power.
Then, the fundamental thing that's done
is, you turn on the lowest-cost units
first.
And you keep turning on units until
you have enough power to meet demand.
So it's always true that
the unit you turn on last,
the unit that you need to turn on,
is the unit that is generating power
at the highest marginal cost.
That highest marginal cost plant
sets the overall marginal power
price on an electric grid.
Here's an example of a dispatch curve
which effectively ranks generators
based on the marginal cost of
generation and the amount of power
they can generate.
So the x-axis shows the total
amount of power generated.
So if you're the operator,
it's the amount of power
that you are requesting from
the system to meet demand.
The y-axis shows the marginal price.
So things that have the lowest
marginal generation costs,
things like renewables or nuclear
power, are far to the left,
at the bottom of the x-axis.
And as you go further
along the x-axis, prices
rise, because you're
getting to generators that
have higher and higher marginal cost.
The big knee in the curve, the place
where the price really skyrockets,
is caused by generators that
burn petroleum, burn fuel oil.
Because fuel oil has a
much higher energy cost
than anything else in the system.
Much higher than the cost
of natural gas, for example.
So suppose you're the operator
of this electric power system,
and at some point, demand is 40 gigawatts.
How do you meet it?
You meet it by turning on
the very cheapest things.
First of all, you turn on
renewables, say, solar and wind.
Those are supplying power at basically
zero marginal cost if the wind is
blowing or the sun is shining.
Then you turn on the next
cheapest things, which
might be nuclear power
plants or hydro plants,
and you turn on just enough
coal to get to 40 gigawatts.
At that point, the price of the most
expensive generator you've turned on,
which, in this example, would
be a coal-fired power plant,
it would have a marginal cost
of, in this example, about $25
a megawatt-hour.
And under the normal way that
electricity markets work,
every generator that you had turned on would
get the same price for electric power.
That price would be determined
by the most expensive generator,
the one you turned on to
meet demand at 40 gigawatts.
And that would be, in this
example, about $25 a megawatt-hour.
Now suppose you have a very hot summer
day, with huge air conditioning loads,
and maybe you've got low wind power output.
So now you need the full 115
or 120 gigawatts of power.
Now, you basically have to turn
on everything in the system,
and that means you're
turning on some things that
have a very high marginal price.
One example would be old-fashioned,
inefficient, oil-fired boilers.
Those oil-fired boilers are expensive
because they have low efficiency,
and expensive because oil is in
energy units of very expensive fuel.
Then, those units would be
setting the overall system power
price, which might be as high as
$200 or more per megawatt-hour.
So that means the hydro
or nuclear generators
would be making a huge profit on that day,
but the system needs to
work that way so in the end,
all operators make enough
money to keep themselves going.
For long-distance, high-power
electricity transmission,
high-voltage DC is the cutting
edge, although, in fact,
the differences between high-voltage
DC and alternating current
are not that big.
To give you a specific example,
the Hami-Zhengzhou line, an HVDC,
high-voltage DC line built in China,
is about 2,200 kilometers in length,
and it transmits eight gigawatts of power,
with 5,000 apps at plus
or minus 800 kilovolts.
These lines are amazingly efficient.
Siemens, a major development of HVDC
technologies, has a rule of thumb
that losses are about
3% per 1,000 kilometers.
So this line is likely nearly
95% efficient in transmitting
eight gigawatts of power more
than halfway across China.
It costs about $3.6 billion US to build,
and it was completed in 2014, after
just under two years of construction.
This cost works out to about $1.6 million
per kilometer, which is
similar to cost estimates
for lines in Europe and North America.
Given typical financial
assumptions which you see here,
the cost of power transmission is
less than 1.5 cents per kilowatt hour.