Welcome to Energy within
Environmental Constraints.
This course focuses on the energy system,
on the nuts and bolts of how it works,
how energy flows from gas wells or wind
turbines through modern economies to
power indoor lighting or heavy trucks.
Not just the flow of materials, but the flow
of money, which determines the
cost of electricity or diesel fuel.
Our goal is not a static
description of the energy system
but rather a description that helps you
understand how it might be improved.
Whether you are working in an
energy company, a government
agency, or an environmental
group, whether you
are a student who hopes to work in energy
or a citizen who cares about
energy in the environment,
you want to figure out how to
make the system work better.
"Better" could mean lots of things--
cheaper, less environmentally
destructive, more profitable,
more secure, or more democratic.
Our focus is on improving the
environmental performance of the energy
system.
That is only possible if you have some
rough understanding of how the energy
system works and its most important
environmental constraints, particularly
air pollution and climate change.
But this is not a broad survey
of energy and the environment.
Our focus is on the energy system
within environment constraints,
which we will teach in less
depth as boundary conditions.
This course aspires to a global perspective
although many of our examples are
drawn from the US energy system,
and it aims to look out over the
next half century or more asking
how the energy system might evolve
to provide energy with a far
smaller environmental impact.
Environment is not the only energy problem.
Before diving in, I want to give
you my view of how environment fits
into the spectrum of energy challenges.
It's useful to think of three
grand energy challenges.
First, energy access.
About 1.3 billion people lack
access to electricity, and roughly 2
and 1/2 billion lack access
to modern cooking technology.
I don't mean fancy induction stoves.
I mean anything other than indoor fires.
Lack of access to these
basic energy services
is a profound impediment
that people struggle
to improve their own well-being.
Without lighting, for example, one
cannot study at night after outdoor
work is done.
Second, energy security.
The links between energy
and conflict are ancient.
The Romans could not have assembled
their armies without an energy system
that moved food and forged metals.
The British decision to
switch to an oil-fired navy
before the First World War
greatly increased the navy's speed
and lethality, but it came
with a political decision
to found the Anglo-Persian Oil Company
based on access to oil fields in Iran--
then partially under British control.
That company is now called
"BP," and oil related conflict
is still central to geopolitics.
Likewise, the links between
nuclear energy and conflict
could hardly be tighter.
Third and finally, energy in the
environment-- the topic of this course.
Air pollution from energy use
kills millions of people each year
worldwide and shortens the lives
of people in polluted cities
by many years.
Carbon dioxide from fossil fuel combustion
is on track to change the world's
climate at a pace and direction
that the planet has not witnessed
for perhaps 55 million years.
The rest of the course will focus on
problems at the intersection of energy
and the environment.
Climate is a topic that draws
many to study energy technology.
I have worked on climate and
energy for half my life, 25 years.
Climate is a huge challenge, but I urge
you not to become a climate monomaniac.
Other energy problems have real human
costs, and reforming the energy system
involves hard choices that
sometimes bring these competing
goals into conflict.
We hope that you will adopt
three broad learning goals as you
work your way through this course.
First, to learn a web of
interrelated facts and skills
sufficient to enable sound judgment
about energy technology and policy.
Of course, you can never know all the facts.
And on this topic, many "facts" aren't.
Lots of facts in the energy world
are contested and uncertain.
But if you know some basic background
information, some reliable sources
of data, and you learn how to make
quantitative estimates about energy
resources, costs, and environmental impacts,
you have the tools to critically
analyze energy challenges
and, thus, to contribute to overcoming them.
Second, to develop a unified
understanding of energy
flows and transformations
in industrial society--
the flows of energy, from
sources like solar or coal,
to end uses, like lighting or air
travel, and the transformations
from coal to diesel fuel or
from electricity to aluminum.
And third, to gain a rough quantitative
overview of some of the most important
links between energy and
environmental systems.
Why exactly do dieselectrics
cause so much air pollution?
How can you estimate the impact of
that air pollution on human health?
How do carbon emissions
today cause climate change
today or in the 23rd century?
How do you compare the cost effectiveness
of different ways of
reducing our climate impact,
say, installing efficient lighting
versus reducing natural gas leaks.