One of the hot topics in
electricity is smart grid,
and this idea sometimes takes
on almost magical properties
and can mean almost anything
in the eyes of its exponents.
There are some ideas
underneath that really matter,
but it's important, first of all, to
say that the existing system we have
is, in many ways, very smart.
It smartly dispatches
a whole complicated set
of interconnected generators to meet demand
and it does it with
extraordinarily high reliability.
So the system already is smart.
The question is how we can
add modern digital tools
to make it a little bit smarter.
And there are several ways
this might happen, all of which
are often called smart grid but
there's no single idea here,
really a collection of ideas.
One example is smart
meters, which would allow
demand in homes or small businesses
to respond to the real time minute
by minute system price.
This would allow demand
centers in those homes--
say, appliances like
refrigerators or central heating--
to respond to the dynamic price.
So for example, your refrigerator
might turn off at just the time
that prices were very high, allowing
the rest the system to respond
more smoothly to some transient.
Another example would be real
time monitoring of power quality
abnormalities, network failures.
And this would allow less need for
technicians to go look for problems.
Another example are new high power
solid state electronic switches
that would allow more fine
grained control of transmission
and distribution infrastructure.
That would allow us to avoid failures better
and to more efficiently
utilize existing hardware.
The combination of better real time
monitoring and more responsive demand
might allow us to use the existing
generating capacity a little bit more
efficiently, perhaps reducing the amount
of so-called spinning reserve, that
is power plants that are
available to meet changes in load
at a moment's notice, limit
that, and still achieve
the same amount of reliability.
Finally, we could imagine more improved
management of numerous distributed
generators.
These changes and more comprise
what's called smart grid.
And there's no doubt that the
grid can get smarter and better,
but it's important to understand
that there's no magic here.
The existing grid already
is quite smart and all
we will do by making it smarter is make
it a little more efficient in the way
power is moved around and the way
demand and supply are matched.
So what price should you,
or perhaps a small business,
get if you generate electricity
locally, say solar on a rooftop,
and feed some power back into the grid?
Net metering is the idea that you would
get paid the same amount per kilowatt
hour that you generate in feed to the grid
as you pay for a kilowatt
hour you use from the grid.
This seems like a fair
deal, but in fact it's not.
It actually hides a big chunk
of the value of the grid itself.
So the actual average power
pool price on the grid,
the price that big generators get,
is significantly lower than the price
you pay.
That difference isn't
some kind of weird profit.
That difference corresponds to the
cost of the entire transmission
and generation infrastructure and
all the backups necessary to make
it work at very high reliability.
A way to see that this is a subsidy
is to imagine the following.
Suppose that over a year, the
average amount of power you use
is zero-- that is, suppose
that at some points
you're using maybe up to 10 kilowatts
of power and at other points
you're feeding 10 kilowatts of power back
to the grid whenever you feel like it.
Under net metering, you'd
pay zero because you'd
be using the same number of
kilowatt hours as you supplied.
But obviously, that doesn't
correspond to the actual value
because you got, by accessing
the grid, the ability
to get 10 kilowatts of power in a
millisecond whenever you want it
and that costs a lot to supply.
For you to get the same level
of reliability yourself,
you'd have to have a very elaborate
and expensive battery backup system.
The distinction is clear when you
look at how big industrial users are
charged for electricity.
They're charged separately for capacity--
that is, the maximum amount of power
they're allowed to draw at any time--
than for average bulk power of electricity
because there are really
two services you're getting.
You're getting the total
number of kilowatt hours
and you're getting the ability to
get a certain number of kilowatts
any time you want it and both
those things are valuable.
So the engineer or economists answer
is that when a small business or home
supplies power whenever
they want to, whatever
they have access to the grid,
the price they should get
is the system's current bulk power
price, not their net metering price.
So in that sense, net metering is a subsidy.
Now, that subsidy may make sense if
there are social reasons that we want
to subsidize distributed generation.
For example, because we want
to put solar power on roofs,
but we need to be clear it is a subsidy.