Here are a couple factors.
First of all, there are
very high fixed costs
and low marginal costs-- factors that
can make a monopoly in any industry.
Second of all, there's that need
to balance supply and demand
second by second in a very
tightly coupled system.
Those two factors make it really impossible
to imagine a completely
free market for electricity.
We can solve that second problem
by having central control.
And indeed all electric power systems
have some form of central control
that defines which generator
turns on and off to meet demand
on a second by second, or at
least minute by minute basis.
Beyond that, there's the problem of
market power that comes from the fact
that a relatively small number of
very large electricity generators
feed very inelastic demand.
This combination means that the
owner of one of those generators
could turn off a generator and
actually drive up the system price
so they make more money overall-- more
money from some other generator they
oww-- in a way that would allow
a certain kind of market power
that is really unacceptable.
So no electric power systems
work as pure free markets.
All of them have deep
complicated regulation.
Here's an example that
illustrates the problem.
Suppose that I own generation assets.
I own a coal plant, which makes power
that's a very low marginal cost.
And I own a oil plant, which makes
power at very high marginal cost.
Suppose that I wait for a day where demand
is very, very high on the system--
perhaps a hot day with lots
of air conditioning load.
And then I turn off my coal plant.
I can tell people it needs
to go down for maintenance.
The system power price will
go up extraordinarily high.
And I'll make so much money on my
oil plant that I'll more the recoup
the fact that I'm not making any money
selling electricity for my coal plant.
That gives an incentive for
gaming that's fundamental.
And we must have regulation
that manages that incentive.
And that regulation is inherently complex.
The basic answer to these problems has been
to run electric power systems
as regulated monopoly utilities.
In these systems, there isn't competition.
One entity runs the system.
The problem with that is that entity
has then no incentive to reduce prices.
So in the classic utility
model, utilities build
and they get what's called
a fixed rate of return.
So that means when they build a generator,
they know exactly what
fraction that generator's cost
they're going to get back.
But what incentive does that give them?
It gives them the incentive
to increase the costs.
So a problem with that classic utility model
is that under a fixed rate of return system,
generators just jack up their costs.
Our problem with a free
market model is gaming.
The electric power system did
not just spring into operation
the last few years.
It's evolved over 125 years.
And it's evolved both in
actual physical infrastructure
in companies that supply
individual pieces of equipment
from generators to long
distance transmission to systems
that use the electricity.
And it's evolved in the legal
and social mechanisms that net
the whole thing together.
So the electric power system
reflects both current technology
and a very long historical evolution.
And that's true most obviously
in places like the United States,
where electric power's been around
since 1882-- the first generator system
that Edison had in New York City.
But it's true even in China, where we're
building out electric power systems
very quickly.
But we're building them out based on
infrastructure and technology that's
been developed over this last century.
So understanding why the system is
the way it is-- why, for example,
is it an alternating current system?
And how we control the system
depends on understanding not just
current technologies, but how the system has
evolved as technologies change
and the institutions that fit
them together changes.
So for example, if you go back to
the beginning of electric power,
the system started first
with Edison's system,
which was a direct current
system that spanned a relatively
small number of city blocks.
It was a low-voltage system that
was a much simpler system to do.
And it was safe.
But with low voltage, the
resistive losses are very high.
And there was a competition between that
and the system devised by Westinghouse,
which was an alternating current system--
a system that had transformers.
So it could do high voltage transmission
and lower voltage distribution.
Those systems battle it out for a while.
And that battle was more than
just a simple technical battle.
But it was a complex
industrial and PR battle.
In the end, the Westinghouse system
won because of the enormous advantages
of the ability to do high voltage low
current long distance transmission.
But now we have a system where more
and more of electric power demand
is actually inherently DC demand--
for computers, for certain kinds
of high power electronic equipment.
And yet the system is locked
into alternating current.
And so here we see by example
ways in which the system reflects
not just current technological realities,
but the long history of its evolution.