DAVID KEITH: electricity system--
the electric power grid is one
of humanity's most amazing inventions.
For example, when the US
National Academy of Engineering
ranked the most important
inventions of the 20th century,
number one on that list was
the electric power system.
This next list of roughly 10 facts
defines how that system works today.
These are not, in fact, all
exactly facts, as we'll discover,
but they are a very good approximation
to the way the electricity system now
works.
First, it is a dense
interconnected network going
between generators and final consumers.
Second, there's no storage.
To a very good approximation, supply and
demand must be instantaneously matched.
In the United States,
for example, the capacity
flowing in and out of all
the combined storage systems
is about 50 times smaller than the peak
capacity to generate power on the grid.
Third, demand is unresponsive.
In the short term, demand
does not respond to price.
This means that electric
power operators work
by forecasting demand, building the
capacity, generators and transmission
systems they need to meet that
demand, and then operating
the system in real time to match demand.
And that means in real time down
to the second to match demand.
Fourth, alternating power grids are dynamic.
They're dynamic beasts with
both elasticity and inertia
and that elasticity and inertia that
comes both from mechanical systems
and electromagnetic systems combines to make
instability, oscillations, oscillations that
could potentially break the system.
This is completely unlike the flow
of data in the internet, where
we can direct exactly where
it goes, or for that matter,
the flow of water in pipes or
natural gas in the gas system.
It is a dynamic system unlike any
other and much harder to control.
It's important to note that the AC
power grid is not one single world grid.
In North America, for
example, there are actually
four independent, synchronous
alternating current grids, east, west,
Texas, and Quebec.
Each of these operates at 60 hertz
but are independently synchronized.
And you can only flow power in
between them with direct current.
Fifth, electricity is in many
senses a natural monopoly.
The very tight coupling
between supply and demand
and the ease in which large suppliers
can gain what's called market power
makes it very hard to have the
traditional free market mechanisms
we see in other parts of the economy.
Sixth, the electrification
of the global energy system
has increased steadily over the last century
and it's a very good bet that this trend
will continue over the 21st century.
The reason is that from the
point of view of a consumer,
whether an individual consumer
or industry, electricity
is such a fantastic energy carrier,
high-powered, controllable, efficient,
and nonpolluting at point of use.
These factors mean that
consumers and industry
will keep using more
electricity as a fraction
of total energy over the next century.
Seventh, right of access-- electricity
is such a necessity for modern life
that we treat it differently
from many other commodities.
If, for example, you don't
pay your bill to Amazon,
Amazon is free in a free market
to stop sending you packages.
Electricity is different.
We regulate it as one of
the necessities and we
make it much harder for an electricity
utility to cut off your power
if you don't pay your bill.
Eighth, the electricity system
depends on a stock of infrastructure,
of capital built up over
decades and decades.
In the US, for example, more than half
of the generating capacity in the US
is greater than 30 years old and
more than 2/3 of the power poles
are also more than 30 years old.
Ninth, electricity
transmission and distribution
is extraordinarily efficient.
In the United States, the system is 94%
efficient and the global average is 92%
So globally, only 8% of
electricity generated
is lost in the transmission
and distribution system.
It's an amazing feat of engineering.
10th and finally, the system
is amazingly reliable.
In the United States, consumers
get power more than 99.95%
of the time and those outages are mostly
local, where, for example, a tree falls
on a distribution pole.
The amount of time that
the whole grid goes down,
that we have interconnected failures,
is extraordinarily infrequent.
Those failures have happened only
once every few decades, on average.
These 10 "facts" should
shape your understanding
of the electricity system.
But of course, not all of
these are strictly true.
The first four particularly
are subject to change
and we'll talk about them
in the rest of this section.
Here's a short walk through a
modern electric power system.
Generators, almost all of which are
turbines, steam, gas, water, or wind,
turn synchronous three-phase
alternating generators that make power.
Transformers then turn that power
from high-current low-voltage
to high-voltage low-current.
The power is moved then by high-voltage
long-distance transmission lines
where other transformers turn it back down
to lower-voltage higher-current power, which
is distributed in intermediate lines.
And then finally, still
other sets of transformers
turn it into lower-voltage power which
goes through final distribution lines
to the end users.
Why the high voltage?
Power is voltage times current.
Suppose you wanted to transmit
one gigawatt of power.
You could do that using one gigavolt and
one amp or using one giga-amp and one
volt. Either of those
would transmit a gigawatt.
But the loss of power in a conductive
line, like a transmission line,
is proportional to I-squared R, the
current squared times the resistance.
So if you double the current, you
lose four times as much power.
This puts a big premium
on running the systems
at low current and low
current means high voltage
for a given amount of power.
So in practice, we run at
higher and higher voltages
when we want to transmit power a long
way because that allows us to transmit
power long distances efficiently.
Well, you can't directly give
consumers the high voltages
we use for transmission.
You'd kill them or blow things
up or in a more pragmatic note,
you'd have to use very thick insulators.
So we need ways in the system to
go between the high voltages we
use for transmission to lower voltages
that we use to actually distribute
power to final consumers.
With alternating current,
you can use a transformer.
A transformer allows you to go
between high-current low-voltage
to high-voltage low-current or vice versa.
And it does this using technology that
actually is 19th-century technology.
They have no moving parts,
they're easy to build,
and large transformers can
be extraordinarily efficient,
more than 98% efficient.
It's the transformer that
works only on AC power,
not DC, that is the ultimate
reason that we have AC power grids.