Will we run out of fossil
fuels, or, more precisely,
will a gradual scarcity of
fossil fuels drive up their price
so that alternatives outcompete them?
Much of our modern thinking about this
is driven by a very famous 1956 lecture
by a petroleum geologist
called M. King Hubbard.
He used a bell-shaped curve to
predict the US oil production
and correctly predicted the peak in 1970.
In 1973, the Arab oil shock
drove fears of oil scarcity
that persist to this day.
But Hubbard did not predict correctly
the future of US oil production
which has since rebounded.
But since that time fears about peak oil,
fears about an end to the
oil age driven by scarcity
have centered around Hubbard's
prediction of a peak.
My view is that we are threatened
more by the abundance of fossil fuels
than by scarcity.
Of course there will be
local scarcity of some fuels,
and there's a turbulence in the push and
pull between oil supply and oil demand.
But there are at least four
forces that in the long run,
suggest that fossil fuels
will be widely available.
The first is technological change.
The second is the geological
diversity of the resource.
The third is price elasticity and
the fourth is inter-fuel substitution
and conversion.
In the next sections, we'll
explore these four factors in order
and look at how they explain the
history of oil production in the world.
First, technological change-- the
technologies for finding and extracting
oil and gas just keep getting better.
Two examples-- one is
the shale gas revolution,
where technologies for
drilling long, horizontal wells
and for making fractures
in precise locations
that allow the oil or gas to seep out
of rock that otherwise would be too
tight, too impermeable to
allow it to flow naturally
have allowed enormous
expansion of US oil and gas
production using new technologies.
Second, the gradual increase
in the size and efficiency
and now automation of mining equipment
allows very large scale coal production
at ever-declining costs.
Second, geological diversity-- when
one hears about an oil resource,
it's very tempting to imagine
a fixed reservoir, like a tank,
and imagine that as that
tank is gradually depleted,
you get to some point where it's all gone.
That's true for some conventional,
so-called volumetric oil reservoirs.
But hydrocarbons occur in
a vast diversity of forms.
There are immense reservoirs, for
example, of Canadian oil or tar
sands that are well-known deposits.
It's easy to know precisely where they are,
but they're very expensive
to extract and turn into oil.
There are other deposits,
like ultra-deep finds
recently made off the coast of Brazil,
where production is well understood,
but finding them is very difficult.
When you look across the whole world,
there is enormous diversity of different
kinds of oil and gas reservoirs.
And that diversity means
that there's no reason
to think about a single fixed supply.
There are larger and larger
supplies of materials
that are harder and harder to get at.
Third, price elasticity-- when prices go
up, people work harder to get the oil.
You can see this in this time series
that shows the oil price along
with the number of working US oil rigs.
See how the to move together.
They're correlated.
Indeed, the technical
definition of oil reserves
is the amount of oil that can be
produced using current technology
at the current market price.
This means that if oil
price suddenly goes up,
oil reserves actually go up overnight,
with no change in technology
and no change in the
actual oil in the ground.
Oil reserves are in this sense
partly an economic definition.
The McKelvey box provides
a good way to think
about the role of price, technology, and
geology in determining the availability
of resource, like oil and gas.
This is a system that's used
by economic geologists studying
both oil and gas and other
resources like, say, minerals.
The vertical axis shows the
cost of producing a resource
with current technology,
while the horizontal axis
shows the certainty the resource
exists-- geological certainty.
So you can think about existing
oil and gas reserves or resources
on these two axes.
The Canadian oil or tar sands, for example,
are geologically certain in that
we know precisely where they are.
But the cost of accessing them, the cost
of extracting that oil from the sands
and turning it into a marketable
product has been very high,
though it's gradually declining
as the technology improves.
Finally, the fourth factor driving
the availability of fossil fuels
is inter-fuel substitution and conversion.
Substitution is when a user, for
example, a electricity plant,
can choose between using
gas or coal and oil.
And so they shift to the cheapest fuel.
This means that when one fuel is
scarce, they can shift to another fuel.
And this provides a kind of economic
interchange between the three fuels,
as well as an economic interchange
when users actually switch.
It's physically possible to
turn one fuel into another.
For example, we can turn coal into
a gaseous fuel, so-called coal
gasification.
And we can turn gaseous fuels into
liquid fuels, so-called gas to liquids.
So in the world today we
both turn coal all the way
into liquid fuels, much higher value
fuels that are used for transportation.
And we turn natural gas into liquid fuels.
This conversion allows
another kind of substitution,
separate from the economic substitution.
It means that even if one
fossil fuel runs short,
for example that we run out
of oil, running out of oil
doesn't mean running out of hydrocarbon
fuels produced from fossil fuels,
because we could produce that
same oil from coal or gas.
To review, we've examined four factors that
shape the long-run
availability of fossil fuels.
First, technological change;
second, geological diversity;
third, price elasticity; and
fourth, inter-fuel substitution.
Together, these have shaped the
history of the oil age since the 1850s.
As an example, look at the
global history of oil production.
Note, for example, that between
about 1930 and 1973, the price of oil
was roughly constant in
inflation-adjusted terms,
while the quantity of oil increased 10-fold.
How did that happen?
It's the story we've been telling, a story
of technological change,
increasing ease of access,
competing against scarcity
of the easy resources.
And over that time period, the
competition between those two
came out about even.
But note the sharp discontinuities--
discontinuities in 1973 and since then
and some discontinuities
in the late 19th century.
Those were caused by regional pushes and
pull, a turbulence between the dynamics
of oil production and oil demand.
There's no doubt that the turbulence
in oil prices will continue.
I don't claim to be able to predict
oil prices a year or five years hence.
A single disaster, natural
disaster or attack on, for example,
the major Saudi loading terminal could
drive oil prices enormously high,
while global economic recession
could drive them much lower.
What these factors do is predict
that the long-run availability
of fossil fuels is large, and that
it's unlikely that in the long run,
sheer scarcity of fossil fuels
will limit our ability to use them,
at least not for centuries.